Dr. Foster S. Brown Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
Dr. Foster S. Brown Papers
1952 - 1963
Under Foster Brown's leadership, the number of students and the physical campus greatly expanded. Brown’s administration saw the opening of Lakeside residence and dining halls, notable academic buildings and Lee Hall’s physical plant (to power the expanding campus) that all lay the foundation for even more growth to come. Brown led the way to the addition of robust liberal arts programs at Oswego to broaden beyond the initial (but still important) teacher preparation focus.
0.67 linear feet
Brown, Foster S.
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2005.054.0001
Collection is open to the public.
Dr. Foster Brown was born in Leyden, New York, on September 18,1908. He graduated from Boonville High School in 1926. He received a B.A. in 1930 and an M.A. in 1933 from St. Lawrence University, Canton, New York, and an Ed. D. in 1950 from Columbia University.
Dr. Foster married Catherine Pickard in 1936. They had five children, Ruth, Susan, Wallace, Celia and Irving. He supported the Boy Scouts of America, was a member of the Rotary Club, Ramapo Valley Children's Service Fund, Rockland County Cerebral Palsy Association, and County Historical Society. He participated in the National Education Association, New York State Teachers Association, Association of State Teachers College Faculties and the American Society for Curriculum Development. His career began as teaching principal at Coeymans, New York in 1930. Dr. Foster worked as teacher and administrator at the State University Teachers College at New Paltz, research associate in the State Education Department and visiting instructor at St. Lawrence University. He was Dean of Cortland State Teachers College from 1951 - 1952.
Dr. Foster Sargant Brown was the sixth president of SUNY Oswego from 1952 until 1963. He then became president of St. Lawrence University in Canton, New York, until he retired in 1970. Dr. Foster died in Chapel Hill, North Carolina on February 14, 1985.
Carlson, William S. (William Samuel), 1905-1994; State University College (Oswego, N.Y.); Oswego (N.Y.); Hunt, Charlotte Alling, 1895-1992; Willgoose, Carl E.; College presidents; Wills and testaments; Basketball -- New York -- Oswego; Mary V. Lee Scholarship Fund -- New York -- Oswego; Alford, Harold D.; Bohall, Hilda C.; Burns, Robert L.; Cooper, Hermann; Dashley, Emily Browning; Davis, George H.; Freeman, Gertrude Laurette; Hallock, Edna J.; Hayes, Katharine A.; Hibbert, Esther; Huss, William Edward; Irland, Mary C.; Jessup, Harriet Foster; Lavenburg, Dolores Elaine; Lavenburg, Helen Irene; Lester, Mabel; Mackin, Marion C.; McFerran, Sadie A.; Osborne, Helen S.; Penney, George M.; Robinson, Ruth Mildred; Rock, Robert; Salander, Carey; Smith, Mary E.; Troy, Donald William; Troy, Thomas Gerald; Turner, Charles; Wells, Charles; Wheeler, Richard C.; Whitten, Norman
Papers include correspondence, memorandums, reports, oral history transcript, newspaper clippings and annual reports.
- Dr. Foster S. Brown, 1952 - 1961 (Box-folder 01-01)
  78 incoming and outgoing letters. Handwritten and typed. Some letters are between Dr. Brown and correspondents while others are between Esther Hibbard (Dr. Brown's secretary) and correspondents. Subjects include alumni, visitors, events, celebrations, Sheldon Hall Inc., list of Utica-area alumni, bequests, Mary V. Lee Memorial Fund and acknowledgements of donations. Correspondents include: Mr. Norman Gover, I. H. Beadle, Esther Hibbard from Sylvanua Milne Duvall, Owen G. Parsons, Reta May Irland Sheldon, Robert C. Meek, Kathryn B. Cameron, Mrs. Robert J. Petermann, Mrs. Ellor C. Ripley, Sadie McFerran Sias, Katharine A. Hays, Thomas Troy, Donald W. Troy, J. H. Couture, George H. Davis, Dolores Lavenburg, Hilda Bohall, Lewis H. Bowen, Emily B. Dashley, George M. Penney, Robert L. Sweeney, Edna J. Hallock-Terry, M. G. Lockwood, William E. Carey, Athena Sawyer, Elizabeth S. Royce, Ruth Dresser Abrams (Ruth Mildred Robinson), Clara Taylor Cornish, Mrs. Jessie Fraser Hayden, Beatrice Wiegand, Virginia S. Baldridge, William D. Conklin, Wallace Geety, Richard C. Wheeler, Gertrude L. Freeman, Marion B. A. Tubbs, Frank G. Carrino, Jonas P. Peterson, (Formerly 1/7/120, folder 3-1. Presidents, Foster S. Brown.)
- Dr. Foster S. Brown, 1958 - 1964 (Box-folder 01-02)
  10 incoming and outgoing letters. Typed and handwritten. Subjects are explanation of donated materials, alumni, citation certificate, and Dean of Students position at St. Lawrence University. Correspondents include: Clara Taylor Cornish, Elizabeth Donovan Bailly, Charlotte Alling Hunt, Charles F. Wells, Robert W. Rock, (Formerly 1/7/92, folder 1-1, Foster Brown.)
- Inauguration + Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1953 - 1963 (Box-folder 01-03)
  May 18, 1953 Inauguration of Foster Sargent Brown papers. Includes Inauguration invitation (4 1/2" x 3 1/2"), Inauguration Dinner program (4 3/4" x 6" bifold), and Inauguration program (2 copies). 6" x 9" bifold. June 7, 1953 Baccalaureate Service program. 5 3/4" x 9" 18-page St. Lawrence University Inauguration publication, "The Inauguration" that includes text and photographs of Dr. Foster's Inauguration for the October 19, 1963 ceremony. Included is a biographical sketch, organization, preparations, and Dr. Brown's address. 8 1/2" x 11" October 21, 1957 letter from Hermann Cooper, Executive Dean, State University of New York requesting a statement from Dr. Foster concerning plans for programs through 1965 or 1970. 2 pages. 2 copies. "Reasons for the institution of a language program at the State University of New York at Oswego". Undated. 1 page. October 30, 1957 letter from Hermann Cooper to Dr. Foster requesting information concerning an over-all program for Oswego by 1970. 7 pages. 2 copies. "Plans for Oswego". 5 pages. 2 copies. (Formerly 1/7/32, folder 1-16, Miscellany, Presidents. Foster S. Brown.)
- Correspondence + related papers, 1959 - 1961 (01-04)
  22 incoming and outgoing letters from college president Dr. Foster S. Brown's office. The correspondence and related papers concern the Indonesia Project. Papers include travel itineraries; lists of names; letters of acknowledgement, appreciation, and thanks; Report to the Research Foundation of the State University of New York on the Inspection of the Existing and Proposed Overseas Projects by Foster S. Brown (12 pages and appendix); students; and F. K. I. P. Correspondents include: Professor Mrs. A. Abas-Manopo, Dean of the F. K. I. P., Medan, Indonesia. Dean Koenjoro, Fakultas Keguruan dan Ilmu Pendidikan, University of Arilangga, Malang, Indonesia. Dr. Apul Panggabean, Educational and Cultural Counselor, Embassy of Indonesia, Washington, D.C. Doedi Soemawidjaja, Educational and Cultural Attache, Embassy of Indonesia, Washington, D.C. Michael Harris, The Ford Foundation, Djakarta, Indonesia. Nienke Soesilowindradini, New York, New York. Professor M. Sadarjoen Siswomartojo, Dean, F. K. I. P., Padjadjaran University, Bandung, Indonesia. Frank T. Lane, Associate Executive Dean, State University of New York. Roger W. Bancroft, Director of Education, State University College of Education, Cortland, New York. Dr. Kuntjoro Purbopranoto, Dean of the Teacher College (F.K.I.P.) of Airlangg, Indonesia. (Formerly 1/7/126, folder 3-1.)
- Correspondence + related papers, 1961 - 1964 (Box-folder 01-05)
  19 incoming and outgoing letters from college president Dr. Foster S. Brown's office. Handwritten and typed. Subjects include the Indonesia project; Annual Report, State University - Ford Foundation, Projects in Indonesia, September 1, 1960 - June 30, 1961 (37pages); "Education in Indonesia" cited "4/11/61 SM" [9 pages]; "Perdjalanan-Djalan" (13 pages, uncited); "The Mountains" (6 pages, uncited); List of Indonesia students at Oswego: Markus Pigawahi, Carolina Juliana Siregar, Soeparman Kardi, Mamad Suhanda, Titus Olembo, Correspondents include: John Slocum, Vice-President for Administration, State University of New York. Beryl Dwight, Liem Tik Liem, Doedi Soemawidjaja, Educational and Cultural Counselor, Embassy of Indonesia, Washington, D.C. R. Murray Thomas, Professor of Education, University of California, Santa Barbara. Charles S. Turner, (Formerly 1/7/126, folder 3-2.)
- Memorandums, SUNY Bond Issue, 1955 - 1957 (Box-folder 01-06)
  March 31, 1955 memorandum from William S. Carlson with 5-page attachment information concerning the State University bond issue. April 12, 1957 memorandum from Jerome G. Kovalcik to Chief Administrative Officer. May 23, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik to Chief Administrative Officers and Public Relations Directors with 5-page attachment of Minutes of Meeting of SUNY Public Relations Council at College of Forestry in Syracuse. August 20, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik to Chief Administrative Officer and Public Relations Personnel with 4-page list of organizations attachment for local SUNY bond-issue campaign. (2 copies of attachment) September 3, 1957 memo from William S. Carlson to Chief Administrative Officers concerning planning conference. September 20, 1957 memo from William S. Carlson to Chief Administrative Officers with campaign contact goals. September 23, 1957 from Carey P. Salander to Dr. Brown. Subject: College personnel breakdown for bond issue information purposes. (3 copies) October 7, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik concerning press kits. October 18, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik. Subject: Bond Issue Campaign. October 21, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik. List of endorsements for bond issue. October 22, 1957 memo from Jerome G. Kovalcik. Subject: Editorials on Amendment No. 1 with 7-page attachment of newspaper clipping photocopies. Includes Buffalo Evening News, Binghamton Sun, Middletown Record, Saugerties Post, Syracuse Herald-Journal, Plattsburgh Press Republican, Endicott Bulletin, Dunkirk Observer, The Ripley Review, Auburn Citizen Advertiser, Schenectady Union Star, New York Times, Buffalo Courier Express, Syracuse Post Standard, Rochester Democrat Chronicle, and Long Island Daily Press. October 30, 1957 memo from President William S. Carlson to Chief Administrative Officers concerning election night. Letter from Harold D. Alford to staff members concerning upcoming vote with attachment of Amendment #1 Promotion Activities. November 6, 1957 memos from Dr. Brown to the faculty, students and employees. concerning the successful vote. (5 copies) (Formerly 1/7/137, folder 4-4. President's Office, Foster S. Brown. Memorandums, SUNY Bond Issue.)
- Correspondence, SUNY Bond Issue, Safety Policy Report, 1954 - 1957 (Box-folder 01-07)
  84 incoming and outgoing letters. Typed and handwritten. Subjects include Citizens Committee for the Bond Issue, Safety Policy, bond issue needs at Oswego, meeting notices, letters to Citizens Advisory Committee and College Council members from James E. Lanigan, postcards in response to James E. Lanigan's letters, Oswego bond issue promotion activities, Correspondents include: Otto Teegan to Daniel B. Webster with 16-page attachment, "Safety Policy Report by Committee on Safety. Carey Salander, William Sample, Mabel Lesher, Joyce Siebers, Louise Hess, William Huss, Archie Wellman, Kenyon W. Warner, Carl E. Willgoose". Jerome Kovalcik, George M. Penney, James E. Lanigan, Marian C. Mackin, R. D. Helsby, Martin Rose, Clarence Leighton, Mrs. Carl A. Manzer, Dr. Harold Sylvester, Anna W. Post, Mrs. Olin J. Mowry, Gladys Morley, W. F. Mitchell, Theodore Menter, Maurice Lockwood, John B. Johnson, Dr. Mark Fitzgibbons, Arthur Chapman, Albert Bradley, Marian R. Steele, Henry A. Wise, Carey P. Salander. Subject: College personnel breakdown for bond issue information purposes. Dr. Hermann Cooper, Richard Wheeler, Thomas Cloutier, Clarence F. Cole, Daniel W. Dougherty, Harold D. Alford, William S. Carlson. 11-page memorandum. Subject: Analysis of Vote on Amendment Number One. Edward F. Crawford, Howard T. Herber, Thomas Cloutier, Hilda Bohall, Clarke Morrison III, Edwin Allen, Clayton Rose, Richard Mandeville. Memorandums and correspondence from Dr. Foster. Letters of appreciation for work done for the Bond Issue. Recipients include: Darvey Carlsen, Warren Smeltzer, Richard Wheeler, Harry Charlton, Ray Page, Fritz Neidhardt, Edward F. Crawford, Henry A. Wise, Leyden E. Brown, John B. Johnson, Father Thomas M. Murphy, and Lawrence O'Brien. (Formerly 1/7/137, folder 4-5 President Office, Foster S. Brown.)
- Inauguration Speech, 1952 (Box-folder 01-08)
  13-page typed speech of Dr. Foster S. Brown. (Formerly 1/7/137, folder 4-10, Foster S. Brown.)
- Robert Burns, Basketball Team, 1958 (Box-folder 01-09)
  1 handwritten letter from Robert Burns (class of 1911) to Dr. Brown, October 22, 1958. Response to letter from Dr. Brown concerning the 1910-1911 Oswego Normal School basketball team. Oswego Normal Basket Ball Schedule, Season 1910-11 publication. 28 pages that are gradually smaller to the center of the booklet. Paper cover. Includes a photograph of the basketball team. There is also a photograph of the interior of John M. Schuler & Son Book and Stationery Store in Oswego, NY. Also advertisements from local businesses, including: The First National Bank, Chrystal's Shoes, John S. Parsons Ship Chandlery, Old Norris Market, The Nacey, A. H. Mowry, G. Meyer, Oswego Hardware Co., D. D. Long, Gilman Davis, Jules Wendell & Son, Hennessey & Dwyer, Fred E. Wells, George W. Bush, Dr. Thomas R. Cullen, The Eureka, L. E. O'Brien, J. M. Riley & Co., The Second National Bank, Kiley Clothing Company, Butler Pharmacy, Frank W. Phillips, O'Brien & Son, The Franklyn, The Hunter Furniture Co., John W. Schaffer, Keating Garage and Engine Co., Leighton Pharmacy, James P. Doyle, James P. Maney, Hunt Bros., Robert Downey & Co., Ould & Co. Clothiers, Burt's Drug Store, The Lake City Print Shop, Glynn's Shoes, Scotch Woolen Co., M. T. Crimmins, Selleck's Shoe Store. 4 newspaper clippings, "Twenty-Five Years Ago" with information about the Oswego Normal School basketball team. Originals and a print of scanned copies. (Formerly 1/7/170, folder 2-30)
- Robert Burns, Basketball Team, 1958 (Box-folder 01-10)
  October 14, 1958 typed letter from Dr. Foster S. Brown to Dr. Robert Burns (1911 Oswego Normal School graduate). Dr. Foster sent Dr. Burns a college newspaper article written by two students, Martin W. Leukhardt and Milena Kovar. Article is 7 pages, typed and uncited. (Formerly 1/7/170, folder 2-31.)
- Opening of College Series, 1960 (Box-folder 01-11)
  June 3, 1960 memorandum to Dean Alford from committee chairman Paul T. Hiser pertaining to New Faculty Orientation. Attached is September 1959 new faculty list. August 3, 1960 memorandum to the faculty from Dean Charles S. Turner with tentative fall 1960 calendar of events for the first 2 weeks of the semester. Fall 1960 Faculty Orientation Program. 2 pages. (Formerly 4/53/104, folder 1-2.)
- Opening of College Series, 1962 (Box-folder 01-12)
  July 5, 1962 memorandum to Dr. Brown from Paul T. Hiser concerning New Faculty Orientation with response memo. August 10, 1962 memorandum to the faculty from Charles S. Turner concerning fall semester opening with attachments. New faculty list and calendar of opening week. Fall 1962 Faculty Orientation program and 2-page list of new faculty members. (Formerly 4/53/104, folder 1-3.)
- Opening of College Series, 1963 (Box-folder 01-13)
  August 8, 1963 memorandum to the faculty from Dr. Brown concerning the choice of an interim president of the college. 2 pages and letter from George M. Penney, Chairman, College Council. College Calendar 1963-1964, Fall Semester. 2 pages. New Faculty statistics. 3 pages. (Formerly 4/53/104, folder 1-4.)
- Chief Administrative Officers, 1952 - 1956 (Box-folder 01-14)
  Meeting minutes of Administrative Staff Meeting, May 27, 1952. 10 pages. Meeting minutes of SUNY Teachers College Presidents with the Executive Dean for Teacher Education. September 1952. 11 pages. Meeting minutes of Lake Placid Meeting of State University Teachers College Presidents. October 1952. 4 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in Rochester. December 1952. 5 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in Albany. February 1953. 5 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in New York City. December 4, 1953. 5 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in Albany. January 14, 1954. 3 pages. Meeting minutes for Administrative Staff meeting in Albany. February 5, 1954. 6 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Staff meeting in Fredonia. May 14, 1954. 7 pages and 6 pages of attachments. Meeting minutes of Administrative Staff meeting in Lake Placid. October 18, 1954. 6 pages. Meeting minutes of SUNY Administrative Conference. January 27, 1955. 7 pages. Meeting minutes of SUNY University Administrative Conference. April 26, 1955. 9 pages. Exhibit 1 memorandum from Alpheus W. Smith to William S. Carlson, Charles H. Foster, Clarke G. Hoffman and Ben A. Sueltz. Subject: Background Statement. June 1955. 2 pages. Exhibit 2 memorandum from Alpheus W. Smith. Subject: Summary of Data. June 1955. 10 pages. Exhibit 3 letter to Charles H. Foster from Alpheus W. Smith. June 1955. Meeting minutes of SUNY Administrative Conference. September 1955. 9 pages. Meeting minutes of SUNY Administrative Conference. December 1955. 12 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in Albany. February 1956. 3 pages. Carbon copy. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference. February 1956. 12 pages. Meeting minutes of Teachers College Presidents in Buffalo. April 1956. 6 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference. May 1958. 11 pages. Report of Mrs. James H. Righter for Group Chairman. Meeting of Councils of State University of New York. June 1956. Buffalo. 3 pages. Meeting minutes of Teacher College Presidents in New York City. October 1956. 11 pages. (Formerly 53/52/102, folder 1-14.)
- Chief Administrative Officers, 1957 - 1962 (Box-folder 02-01)
  Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference in Albany. January 1957. 26 pages. Agenda for New Paltz College camp conference. April 1957. 4 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference in Maritime College, Fort Schuyler, NY. April 1957. 10 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference in Albany. October 1957. 7 pages. Meeting minutes of State University Teachers College Presidents in New Paltz. November 1957. 4 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference at Racquet Lake. September 1958. 4 pages and 5 pages of attachments. Meeting minutes of Presidents of Colleges of Education and Harpur College and Dean of the College of Forestry. Albany. February 1960. 6 pages. Meeting minutes of Administrative Conference at Albany. February 1960. 9 pages. Meeting minutes of Presidents of Colleges of Education, Harpur College and College of Forestry at Albany. January 1961. 8 pages. Minutes of College Presidents meeting. March 1961. 4 pages. Meeting minutes of Chief Administrative Officers of Colleges of Education, College of Forestry, and Harpur College at New Paltz College Camp. July 1961. 4 pages. Meeting minutes of Presidents of State University Colleges and Harpur College at New Paltz. November 1961. 8 pages. "Administrative Positions Required to Provide Essential Professional Services for Faculty and Students" by Foster S. Brown. Prepared for New Paltz Conference. September 1962. 13 pages. Also includes various memorandums, agendas, and meeting announcements pertaining to some of the meetings. (Formerly 53/52/102, folder 1-15.)
- Memoranda, 1959 - 1963 (Box-folder 02-02)
  Memorandum from Foster S. Brown to the faculty. April 1959. Re: Promotions for September 1959. List of professors and new positions. 2 pages. Includes Seward Salisbury, Carlton Gerbracht, Francis Hulme, George Pitluga, Dorothy Rogers, Norris Goldsmith, James Hastings, William McGarvey, Erwin Palmer, Virginio Piucci, Owen Pittenger, Robert Babcock, Frederick Winn, Willard Allen, Helen Buckley, Frank Scholfield, Verna Bergemann, Paul Goodwin, Charles Shoemaker, Matilda Wordelman, Raymond Bridgers, Robert Frumkin, William Hanks, Walter Nitardy, Marguerite Roberts, John Somerville, Kathryn Vacha, John Walcott, Richard Wheeler, George Nikas, and Frederick Maxon. Letter to the Members of the Class of 1959 from President Foster S. Brown. 1 page. Memorandum from Dr. Brown to the faculty. August 1963. This is his last administrative memo to the faculty. 2 pages. (Formerly 4/41/107, folder 2-3.)
- Predecessor Records, 1955 - 1963 (Box-folder 02-03)
  Incoming memorandums to college president Foster S. Brown. Correspondents include Norman E. Whitten, Deans of Students, Charles F. Wells, and Robert Rock. Subjects include the local community, Niagara Mohawk lease, Admissions, rules of conduct, proposed golf putting green, use of university facilities, exchange student group, admissions procedure for veterans, student meetings with college president, OSTC Foundation and Fallbrook Farm, washing machines in residence halls, repairs to college union, Hillcrest Hall head resident, letter to parents of students who resided in Archer House, campus telephone services, student health requirements, college union coat room, campus visitors, senior placement folder material, pedestal lighting for lakefront area, student orientation, refinishing dormitory student furniture, milk cooler at dining faciltiy, dish machines at Hillcrest and Kingsford Halls, money for medicines and drugs in budget, coal delivery to Fallbrook, dormitory furniture, tuition, room rents, loans, voting machines, foreign student advisory program, new assistant Dean 1 position for Lonis and Moreland Halls, intramural althletics, alumni scholarship fund, assistant deans of students, state of Federal Loan account, married student housing survey, resident hall statistics, and unregistered senior activies. (Formerly 32/1/107, folder 1-26.)
- Chapters, 1957 - 1961 (Box-folder 02-04)
  6 incoming and outgoing letters. Typed and handwritten. 1957 letter from Athena F. Sawyer to Dr. Foster Brown pertaining to California Alumni Chapter of Oswego State Teachers College. 1957 letters between Edythe Carey and Dr. Brown concerning Dr. Brown's invitation to the Southern Tier Alumni Spring Banquet. 1959 letter from E. L. Gardner, Executive Secretary, to Beatrice Wiegand with 2-page names list of Oswego Alumni California Chapter. 1961 letter to Vernon A. Tryon from Richard C. Wheeler, Administrative Assistant, with 3-page attachment of Dr. Brown's typed message to Washinton, D.C. area alumni group. 1961 letter from Vernon A. Tryon to Dr. Brown with 2-page attachment with invitation to Washington, D.C. area alumni Christmas party. (Formerly 31/7/120, folder 3-5.)
- Newspaper Clippings + Oral History Transcript, 1959 - 1978 (Box-folder 02-05)
  4 copies of Oswego, New York, newspaper clippings pertaining to Dr. Brown. April 25, 1959, "Dr. Brown Going to Indonesia On Eight-Week Tour". April 1959 newspaper clipping [not cited]. Correspondence from Dr. Brown to Thomas Beard of the Oswego YMCA. Also includes photograph of Dr. Brown December 19, 1963, "Dr. Foster Brown Inaugurated As President at St. Lawrence". "St. Lawrence President To Succeed Foster S. Brown". April - June 1969. Fulton newspaper clipping of Mrs. Foster S. Brown's obituary. Copy of oral history (OH 117) transcript of Dr. Foster's narration of S.U.C.O. campus recorded in 1978. 12 pages.
- Foster S. Brown, 1950 - 1969 (Box-folder 02-06)
  See 2005.054.0002 for detailed description of the 17 photographs.